good evening and thank you to Jesse
Turner and John Foshay for inviting me
here tonight and I thank you all for
coming Experiment
math is cultural that's not a question
it just says let's do an experiment this
is the scenario I'm in otavalo Ecuador
and I don't speak Spanish and the vendor
doesn't speak English but I want six
oranges so I want everyone in the
audience to show me six with your
fingers hold them up in the air let's
see how you show six Wow look around see
the variety so we have six this way and
we have six this way and we even have
six this way
in Zulu you can put your hands down
in Zulu six literally means take the
thumb in Tanzania and Western and Rwanda
in Western Tanzania you might even see
six this way and I know some people had
this and they wondered yes I saw you a
okay as it turns out finger gestures are
very cultural in nature and if you think
about it counting is one of the most
basic things one of the most basic
mathematics activities that a culture
can do well today I'm going to talk
about culturally relevant pedagogy in
terms of mathematics right so culturally
relevant pedagogy teaching is a pedagogy
that empowers students and empowers them
intellectually socially emotionally and
politically and I really like that one
by using cultural reference to impart
knowledge skills and attitudes. Culturally Relevant Pedagogy
first of all students come to school to
learn we know that but we also know as
educators that what students learn in
the classroom is not all there is
Johanna Hayes our Teacher of the Year
and she's from Waterbury Connecticut she
really believes that it takes more than
what you do in the classroom and so I
agree with that and I think most
educators know that Gloria
ladson-billings says culturally relevant
teaching has three criteria one is is
that students have academic success so
it's not enough for the access we need
the attainment to that students have
cultural competence but let's face it we
are also hearing that teachers need
cultural competence as well and finally
that children develop a critical
consciousness we have to help students
and this is where the politically comes
in we have to help students understand
and be empowered to challenge the status
quo lots and billions goes on to say Social Context
that schools you sometimes often do not
really support culturally different
students because they don't provide a
social context for learning where
students can have access to the
knowledge and a comfortable in a
familiar way and we heard earlier in a
safe way so the question is can we teach. The Question
mathematics in a way that students can
connect to themselves and to their
communities and to their identity can we
teach in a way that empower students to
challenge injustice
and most of all can we teach in a way
that honors students and their cultural
and their intellectual greatness there's
a lot being said there so let's think
about this if we want to empower
students the task in our classroom have
to change right so the current
curriculum we have is just not gonna do
it oh I want to tell you about my young Real Life Stories
lady there so she participates in a
Saturday STEM program and I worked with
a group of students there to create
clocks for Benjamin Banneker day and
that particular day they were able to
use mathematics equations to go around
the hands of the clock and also just to
show their artistic side and she of
course is very artistic so Geneva gay
says that every student has a strength
every student does something well and
that's what we have to start with so
here are some real life stories if we
want to connect the students these are
some of the things that we could do
these are researchers that do that do
math for social justice and culturally
relevant math bill Tate worked with the
teacher to do a project with students to
sort of learn about their community and
what they wanted to do was to count the
number of liquor stores in their
neighborhood and they did that they took
a walk around their community and then
they took the bus to the suburban
community and they counted the number of
liquor stores or package stores if we
want to say it nicely in that
neighborhood and they found out to their
surprise that there were a lot more
liquor stores in their neighborhood and
so they wrote their City Council there's
the politically again right so when I
first started teaching I I didn't know
about that word politically I said
that's not my place but what I'm
learning is
that it is my place and so anyway these
students wrote a letter to their City
City Council and they asked to close 13
liquor stores that were in 1,000 feet of
their school how they know that they did
the research
so students are learning and they're
dealing with issues from their community
and they're using math they use
percentages decimals and fractions to
make their case to the City Council and
they were successful somewhat not
totally they didn't close 13 liquor
stores but they were somewhat successful
the other picture with the quilts a
Jacqueline Leonard and her colleagues
worked with fourth-grade teachers in
Philadelphia and they wanted to
incorporate culturally relevant teaching
and their reading and in their math
classroom and so what they did was they
made quilts so the students were able to
be artistic they were able to tell the
story because a quote tells the story
about your life so they were able to
talk about themselves and the teacher in
fact learned a lot about the students
that she didn't already know the other
thing is they learn area and perimeter
so we're still doing the math right when
Gloria ladson-billings said we have to
have academic success she didn't mean we
were going to do culturally relevant
math and dumb down the math we're still
gonna do math that is complex that gets
students thinking and also that sort of
hit the standards whatever those might
be because all teachers have to think
about that
the last picture shows corn rolls and I
had a colleague talk to me about a week
ago and she had a math lesson that she
wanted to do that involved corn rolls
and she has an african-american female
student in her classroom well she didn't
feel it was her place to just pick that
particular student out so she emailed
the whole class and said do you know
anyone that knows how to do corn rolls
and would they mind speaking to our
class low and behold that student
thought come
enough to leave that class discussion
and this was a student who normally
would sit in the back of the room and
not be engaged and so the teacher told
me that story because she was really
happy about it but also she tried
something new she did a math lesson
about corn rolls and there's actually a
book it's called math as a verb and it
has a full lesson on just corn rolls and
there's of course other culturally
relevant lessons in there as well so The Framework
we're always trying to connect to our
students and so my colleagues and I
created or put forth a framework for
culturally relevant cognitively
demanding math tasks and what we did was
we started with the literature on
culturally relevant teaching and then we
added in the literature on cognitively
demanding tasks mary-kate Stein and her
colleagues helped us with that and from
that we were able to come up with a
framework that could assist teachers in
making culturally relevant lessons and
so this is one of the tasks that
teachers create it and I loved it I
thought of the students I used to teach
right away because I thought of tagging
and I thought of Christmas
graffiti but one of the things that the
teachers learned was that a task is not
culturally relevant in itself it depends
on the students so for me this was
culturally relevant for my students but
for another colleague they didn't feel
it was culturally relevant at all and by
the way this particular task gets at
domain and range it gets at graphing on
a coordinate plane it gets that ratio
and proportion and using a scale factor
in order to reduce sorry reduce our or
enlarge the picture. Moving Forward
so how do we move forward so teachers
trying to find resources that would help
them to create culturally relevant
mathematics tasks they could look at Bob
Moses he talks about math being a civil
rights issue and what he talked about
was how algebra has been a gatekeeper
and how even in the car at the college
level how some students have to take
algebra two and three times in order to
graduate college so it is indeed still a
gatekeeper it keeps some students from
really reaching their goals and then we
have other people like Gloria
ladson-billings who talked about
teachers that were successful with
african-american students and then we
talked about Peterson and guts teen or
gutes teens scuse excuse my
pronunciation who talked about math for
social justice and and they have a
lesson in their book called buying a
home while black or brown I love it it's
for high school students and they get to
read statistics about what is really
happening when people go out and
purchase try to purchase a home depends
on the neighborhood right and then
finally I have a math and culture and
popular media and I like that resource
by Chappell and Thompson excuse me
I like that resource because it brings
in popular media and so we can watch a
clip from a movie like The Pursuit of
Happyness
and she has lessons to go with that and
so how will you move forward and I and
this is what I say to you to move
forward this is what you want to do you
want to remember what cred Dotson says
he says in our classroom we don't teach
math we teach children just think about
that we teach children we want to
empower them we want them to be
academically successful we want them to
be culturally competent and so we think
of all of these things
and there was one slide that I want to
go back to because I do have one more
minute and I just wanted to say that we
also created a rubric to help teachers
assess the level of cultural relevance
so for instance in one of the
characteristics of a culturally relevant
tasks you have students will critique
Society
well we don't do that very much in math
and it's actually okay that we don't but
maybe we want to do it sometimes
or one of the one of the characteristics
is that we use students knowledge in in
knowledge of their community and math
lessons and so these are some of the
tools that teachers can use to help them
create culturally relevant math tasks to
use culturally relevant math tasks and
to engage students give them an entry
point into math because as we know math
is cultural thank you